Finding Aid for Department of Political Science (University of Michigan) records, 1910-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Political Science (University of Michigan) records 1910-2009 1970-2000
University of Michigan. Department of Political Science.
9720 Bimu 2
The Department of Political Science was established in 1910 under the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts; offers coursework in American politics, comparative politics, world politics and international relations, political theory, law and courts, and methodology. The collection spans from 1910-2009 with a bulk of the material from 1970-2000. These records document the administrative functioning of the department and contain committee meeting minutes, information on courses and degrees, departmental meeting minutes, information on faculty, various topical files, and audio-visual material.
12 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Department of Political Science in December 1996 and May/June 2000. An addition was made in 2013. (Donor No. 2184 )
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
Although the Department of Political Science was not formally established until 1910, courses in what came to be known as the field of political science have been taught at the University of Michigan since 1860, when Thomas McIntyre Cooley began to offer classes on the Constitution within the Law Department. After 1865, courses in government were offered in the Department of History, reflecting the focus of history on political institutions, individuals, and events. Within this department, Charles Kendall Adams taught lecture courses in the growth of liberty in England and the history and characteristics of the Constitution of the United States. From 1872 to 1910, President James B. Angell taught classes in Public International Law and the History of Treaties which were available to students in both the Law Department and the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A). In 1881, a School of Political Science was formed within LS&A with Adams as dean. The new school combined the curricula taught by these three men with other topics such as political economy, social science, sanitary science, comparative administrative law, and forestry administration. The school only lasted through the 1887-1888 academic year, however, dissolving as a result of administrative difficulties and the departures of Adams to Cornell in 1885 and temporarily of Cooley to the Interstate Commerce Commission in 1887.
Once the School of Political Science was discontinued, courses in this subject were again taken over by the history department. With the retirement of President Angell in 1909, it was determined that a new faculty member should be appointed to teach his courses and this process led to the establishment of a new department within LS&A. In 1910, the Department of Political Science was established with Jesse Siddall Reeves appointed as its first professor. Reeves taught courses in American Government, Municipal Government, Public International Law, and the History of American Diplomacy. The courses proved quite popular and faculty appointments and student enrollment increased for several years. Joseph Hayden was the first to receive a Ph.D. from the department in 1915. The Center for Political Studies was formally created in 1970 within the Institute of Social Research with Professor Miller serving as the first director. In 1976, President Gerald R. Ford was appointed as an adjunct professor and came to campus to give presentations on foreign policy. In 1990, the chair of the department, Jack Walker, died in a car crash, which caused the Undergraduate Affairs Conference to be renamed the Walker Conference.
In 1997 U.S. News and World Report ranked the department as number one in the field of American government and politics, and second for its overall program. The department currently teaches courses within six major fields of political science: American politics, comparative politics, world politics and international relations, political theory, law and courts, and methodology.
Department of Political Science Chairs
1910-1937 Jesse Siddall Reeves
1937-1944 Joseph R. Hayden
1944-1947 Everett S. Brown
1947-1961 James K. Pollock
1961-1964 Arthur W. Bromage
1964-1970 Samuel J. Eldersveld
1970-1971 Donald G. Stokes
1972-1977 Harold K. Jacobson
1977-1982 Samuel H. Barnes
1982-1989 John W. Kingdon
1990-1993 Arlene Saxonhouse
1993-1999 John E. Jackson
1999-present Daniel H. Levine
The records of the Department of Political Science document its administrative functions from 1910 to 2009 and the bulk of the records date from 1970 to 2009. The record group is divided into seven series: Committees, Correspondence, Course and Degree Information, Departmental Meetings, Faculty, Topical Files, and Audio-Visual.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; Political science--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.
- Committees
  The Committees records (3.5 linear feet, 1972-2004) primarily include information from the Executive Committee, including meeting agendas and minutes, election results, memoranda, correspondence, and reports. For the years 1972-1982 the records are arranged chronologically by school year and are divided into five sections within each year: "Organization," "Agendas," "Minutes," "Documents," and "Miscellaneous." For the years 1989-1994, the records are arranged chronologically by month of the school year. Other committee information is included in the record group, most notably information on the activities of the Graduate Affairs Committee.
  - Committee Assignments 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee
    - 1972-1976, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - 1976-1982, 5 folders (Box 2)
      (the following subdivisions are made within each school year: Organization, Agendas, Minutes, Documents, Miscellaneous)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1987 (Box 2)
      (subdivided by school year)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
      (subdivided by individual meeting date)
    - 1987-1994 (Box 3)
    - September 1988-February 1993, 40 folders (Box 3)
      (subdivided by month)
    - March 1993-April 1994, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - Elections 1973-1995 (Box 3)
  - Foreign Area Studies Advisory Committee 1982, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Graduate Affairs Committee 1970-1986, 1988-1990, 1992-1997, 1999, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Institute of Public Policy 1970-1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Program Evaluation Committee 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Undergraduate Admissions Literature Committee 1985 (Box 4)
  - Undergraduate Affairs Committee 1985-1999, 2004 (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1.25 linear feet, 1972-1996) contains various communications between members of the department faculty and other faculty in the University as well as correspondence with people outside the University.
  - Barnes, Samuel 1980 (Box 4)
  - Cather, James 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Chamberlin, John 1991-1995 (Box 4)
  - Chips, Bob 1983-1988 (Box 4)
  - Cross, John 1987-1996, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Duderstadt, James 1987-1988, 1991-1993 (Box 4)
  - Goldenberg, Edie 1990-1996, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Graduate Students 1990-1996 (Box 4)
  - Halloway, Henry 1984, 1987, 1991-1995 (Box 4)
  - Jacoby, Robin 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Jonides, John 1990-1992 (Box 4)
  - Kinder, Donald 1979-1980, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Ledbetter, Robert 1972-1989 (Box 5)
  - Leverette, Bland Jr. 1973-1982 (Box 5)
  - Marino, Joseph 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Martin, Michael 1992-1994 (Box 5)
  - McDonald, Terry 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Meiland, Jack 1983-1993, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Murphy, Barbara 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - Pierce, Roy 1991 (Box 5)
  - Rasmussen, Paul 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Saxonhouse, Arlene 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - Schoem, David 1985-1995 (Box 5)
  - Steiner, Peter 1973-1978, 1981-1987, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Swain, Mary Ann 1991 (Box 5)
  - Uher, Ctirad 1992-1994 (Box 5)
  - Walker, Jack 1975, 1981-1988, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Whitaker, Gilbert 1991-1994 (Box 5)
- Course and Degree Information
  The Course and Degree Information series (1.5 linear feet, 1910-2009) contains course guides, handbooks, and various materials related to information about the department's courses and degree programs. Of particular note is the statistics on all students who have received a Ph.D. from the department from 1910 to 2009.
  - American Institutions Courses 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - American Political Science Review Dissertations 1948-1955, 1958-1964, 1970-1977, 1980-1983, 1986-2000, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Center for Judaic Studies 1993 (Box 5)
  - Comparative Politics Internship 2002-2003 (Box 5)
  - Comparative Politics Subfield 1988-1996 (Box 5)
  - Course Enrollment Summary 1987 (Box 6)
  - Course Evaluation 1975-1983, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Course Guide 1979-1989, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Curriculum Survey 1975-1976 (Box 6)
  - Degree Statistics 1970-1978, 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - Degrees Awarded 1911-1996 (Box 6)
  - Department Concentrations 1966-1993, 2004 (Box 6)
  - Dissertation List 1911-1960, 1970-1994, 1996-2000, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Enrollment History 1970-1980, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Graduate Association of Political Science 1969 (Box 6)
  - Graduate Course Guide 1990 (Box 6)
  - Graduate Program Reports 1969-1971 (Box 6)
  - Graduate Program Statistics 1966, 1969, 1978-1985, 1987-1990, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - Graduate Student Guide 1988, 1990-1992, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Institute of Public Policy Studies 1972-1982 (Box 6)
  - Law and Politics Subfield 1992-1994 (Box 6)
  - Law School 1991, 1995 (Box 6)
  - PhD Program Guidelines 1940-1971, 1978, 1993, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - PhD Recipients 1910-2009 (Box 7)
  - Specialized Master's Degree 1976-1977 (Box 7)
  - Statistics Tables 1971-1974 (Box 7)
  - Student Attitudes Towards Graduate Program 1969 (Box 7)
  - Undergraduate Funding 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - Undergraduate Student Handbook undated (Box 7)
  - UPSA (Undergraduate Political Science Association) Course Guides and Events 1991-1998 (Box 7)
  - UPSA Student Questionnaire 1982 (Box 7)
  - Undergraduate Program Guidelines 1985, 1988 (Box 7)
  - University Course 299 "Race, Racism, and Ethnicity," 1991 (Box 7)
  - World Politics 1971-1978 (Box 7)
- Departmental Meetings
  The Departmental Meetings series (1.0 linear foot, 1972-1988) contains the agendas, minutes, and attachments of the monthly meetings of the faculty and selected members of the graduate and undergraduate student associations of the department. The records are arranged chronologically. The departmental meetings typically involved debating matters directly affecting the department such as policies and procedures, faculty recommendations, and making final decisions on student and curricular matters.
  - Minutes and Background Material
    - 1972-1974 (Box 7)
    - 1974-1977 (Box 7)
    - 1977-1984 (Box 7)
    - 1981-1985 (Box 7)
    - 1985-1988 (Box 8)
- Faculty
  The Faculty series (.75 linear feet, 1945-2004) primarily includes general information regarding the faculty of the department, faculty organizations, policies, and lists of faculty and their concentrations. Also included is data on faculty salaries.
  - Academic Personnel 1972-1980 (Box 8)
  - Employment Procedures 1980 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Appointments 1980-1982 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Award Nominations 1955-1995 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Cohort Study 1986 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Field List 1981-1983 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Marshall 1991 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Policies 1983, 1987, 1990-1995, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Review Schedule 1982-1983 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Salary Data 1945-1969, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Faculty-Staff Listings 1971-1974, 1984-1995 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Survey 1982-1984 (Box 8)
  - Fifield, Russell 1949-1983 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Instructional Staff of Color 1992 (Box 8)
  - Leave Funds 1987, 1990-1995 (Box 8)
  - Lump Sum Advance Request 1982-1983 (Box 8)
  - Meyer, Alfred 1994 (Box 8)
  - Office Personnel 1973-1980 (Box 8)
  - Senior Secretary Position 1981 (Box 8)
  - Staff Benefits 1981-1984 (Box 8)
  - Staff Salary Program 1976-1982 (Box 8)
  - Tanter, Raymond 2004 (Box 8)
  - Voting Faculty 1983-1984 (Box 8)
  - Weiss, Janet 1979-1981 (Box 8)
  - Women's Caucus 1969-1981 (Box 8)
- Topical Files
  The Topical File series (3 linear feet, 1910-2009) contains various records that pertain to issues and events occurring in the Department of Political Science. Of particular importance are the three files that contain the schedules, correspondence, and other materials relating to President Gerald R. Ford's several visits to campus as an adjunct professor in the Department of Political Science. The series also contains a large segment on the statistics of the department, such as the number of students enrolled, their gender and ethnicity, and their focus within the field of political science. Other files include departmental reviews, the renovation of Haven Hall, and copies of the departmental newsletter, The Satellite.
  - General Department Information (Box 9)
  - Affirmative Action Program 1976 (Box 9)
  - Allocations 1987-1995 (Box 9)
  - Alumni Responses 1997-1999 (Box 9)
  - Alumni Survey 1976 (Box 9)
  - Askwith Distinguished Service Award 1992-1996 (Box 9)
  - Authorized Strength 1990 (Box 9)
  - Black Staff and Student Recruitment 1971-1976 (Box 9)
  - Brochures 1941, 1958 (Box 9)
  - Budget 1965-1979, 1981-1985, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Center for Public Affairs 1988 (Box 9)
  - Chairman's Letters 1978-1989 (scattered) (Box 9)
  - Comparative Departmental Data 1987 (Box 9)
  - Consortium for Political Research 1974-1975 (Box 9)
  - Department Administration Effort Report 1973-1980 (Box 9)
  - Department of Education Material 1981 (Box 9)
  - Department External Review 1992-1993, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Department Funding 1993 (Box 9)
  - Department Publicity 1972, 1987, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Department Ranking 1991-1995 (Box 9)
  - Department Review Board Questionnaire 1985 (Box 9)
  - Department Statistics 1953-1969, 1972, 1974-1980, 7 folders (Box 9)
  - Department Statistics 1980-2002, 21 folders (Box 10)
  - Department Strategic Plan 2002 (Box 10)
  - Detroit Area Study 1976-1977, 1987 (Box 10)
  - Diversity in the Department of Political Science 1993 (Box 10)
  - Donald Rhodes Memorial Fund 1980-1983 (Box 10)
  - Eldersveld, Sam 2006 (Box 10)
  - English Composition Board 1981-1982 (Box 10)
  - Entry Restriction Verification 1981 (Box 10)
  - External Review 1993 (Box 10)
  - Ford Presidential Library 1980 (Box 10)
  - Ford Visits
    - April 1977, 1976-1978 (Box 10)
    - November 1977 (Box 10)
      (contact sheets, negatives are in UM. New and Information Services, Series C, Box C35)
    - March 1979 (Box 10)
  - Fundraising 1995 (Box 10)
  - Haven Hall Renovation 1980, 1982-1987, 1990-1994, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Haven Hall Renovation Blueprints (Box 10)
  - Henry Russell Award 1982-1985, 1990 (Box 10)
  - History of the Department (Box 10)
  - Irwin and Janet Robinson Scholarship Fund 1972 (Box 11)
  - Jack Walker Eulogies 1990 (Box 11)
  - James K. Pollock Reading Room 1975-1977, 1980, 1984 (Box 11)
  - Lecture Fund 1975-1991, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Micro Computer Survey 1984 (Box 11)
  - Midwest Political Science Conference 1989-1990, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
  - Minority Students 1970-1973 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous 1983-1997 (scattered dates) (Box 11)
  - National Commission on the Public Service 1988 (Box 11)
  - National Medal of Science Award 1991-1993 (Box 11)
  - National Science Foundation Project Survey 1980-1981 (Box 11)
  - Nature of the Chairmanship 1972 (Box 11)
  - Neil Staebler Fund 1989 (Box 11)
  - Political Science News 1988-1990, 1998-2009 (Box 11)
  - Public Service Commission 1987-1988 (Box 11)
  - Regents Communication 1992-1993 (Box 11)
  - Report of Activities of the Department of Political Science 1954-1958 (Box 11)
  - Reports 1969-1974 (Box 11)
  - Research Center for Black Mental Health 1987 (Box 11)
  - The Satellite 1987, 1989-1992 (Box 11)
  - Sexual Harassment Policy 1990-1995 (Box 11)
  - Sexual Harassment Workshops 1991-1995 (Box 11)
  - Squier, John (Box 11)
  - Target of Opportunity Program 1991 (Box 11)
  - Teaching Assistance Program 1986 (Box 11)
  - United Nations Model Conference 1978-1982, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Women's Caucus Complaint 1976 (Box 11)
- Audio-Visual
  The Audio-Visual Material series (1.0 linear foot, 1943-1998) contains recordings of prominent lectures and awards ceremonies in the Department of Political Science. The most extensive portion of the collection is the audio recordings of the many lectures given by President Gerald R. Ford during his campus visits.
  - VHS Videotapes (Box 12)
    - Professor Al Meyer receiving Grand Order of the Cross Award April 10, 1991 (Box 12)
    - Walker Conference: Politics (or unpolitics) of Unemployed and Underclass (Undergraduate Political Science Association) 1992, 2 tapes (Box 12)
    - Sixth Annual Jack L. Walker Conference: The Role of Abortion as a Political Issue March 23, 1993 (Box 12)
  - Audio Cassettes
    - Dictation of letters from Professor William B. Ballis to Professor Knott, Dean of LS&A circa 1980, 2 audiocassettes (Box 12)
    - President Ford Lectures
      - November 2, 1977
        - PS 415 American Chief Executive (8:30-9:30am) (Box 12)
        - PS 410: American Policy (10:00-11:00am) (Box 12)
        - PS 483: American Political Parties (1:00-2:00pm) (Box 12)
      - November 3, 1977
        - PS 496 Electoral Behavior (8:00-9:00am) (Box 12)
        - PS 417 Legislative Process (9:00-10:00am) (Box 12)
        - Special Energy Seminar (2:00-4:00pm) (Box 12)
      - November 4, 1977
        - Bentley Library Panel Discussion (10:00am-12:00pm), 2 tapes (Box 12)
        - Combined PoliSci Classes (PS 611, PS 615, PS 683) (2:00-3:30pm) (Box 12)
      - March 1, 1979
        - Foreign Relations and International Politics (PS 160, PS 464, PS 471) (3:00pm) (Box 12)
      - March 2, 1979
        - Foreign Policy Graduate Seminar (10:30-11:30am) (Box 12)
        - National Domestic Policy Formation and Administration (PS 431, 434, 436) (2:00-3:00pm) (Box 12)
    - Interview of Professor Nancy Burns, Professor in the Department of Political Science, early 1990s (Box 12)
    - Radio Liberation Program: Dialectic Materialism (Soviet Propaganda) undated (Box 12)
    - Women in the Academy: Speaker Arlene Saxonhouse May 15, 1998 (Box 12)
  - 1/4" Reel-to-Reel Audio Tape
    - Professor William Ballis Lectures
      - Soviet Foreign Relations until World War II, summer 1962 (Box 12)
      - The Future of the Soviet Union, probably summer 1962 (Box 12)
      - Soviet Foreign Policy 1943-present 1960-1965s (Box 12)
        (Lecture given probably in early 1960s, coincides with International Peace Festival in Helsinki; Khrushchev still in power)
      - Ballis Lecture at City Club, June 26 (Box 12)
        (no year indicated)
      - Ballis Lecture (Box 12)
        (illegible title)
Related Material
For related material on political science, researchers may wish to consult the following collections held at the Bentley Library:
College of Literature, Science and the Arts
School of Political Science (Bimu C26/1)
Thomas McIntyre Cooley Papers, 1850-1898
James Kerr Pollack Papers, 1920-1968
Jesse Sidall Reeves Papers, 1853-1954
A.F.K. Organski Papers, 19591-1998
Alfred G. Meyer Papers, 1924-1998
Arthur W. Bromage Papers, 1917-1979
J. David Singer Papers, 1947-1997
Harold M. Door Papers, 1922-1973
Joseph Ralston Hayden Papers, 1854-1948
Warren E. Miller Papers, 1950-1980
Thomas H. Reed Papers, 1902-1971
Samuel James Eldersveld Papers, 1957-1959
Philip E. Converse papers, 1948-1989
Michel Oksenberg Papers, 1960-1992
Lynn W. Eley Papers, 1958-1963
Lionel H. Laing Papers, 1943-1962
Everett Somerville Brown, 1923-1955
George Ludwig Grassmuck, 1960-1971
Lawrence Preuss, 1945-1954